<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the King at White-Hall November 5, 1684 / by Francis Lord Bishop of Ely ...</title>
            <author>Turner, Francis, 1638?-1700.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63884</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3285</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1832</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12242408</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12242408</idno>
            <idno type="VID">56824</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63884)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 56824)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 901:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the King at White-Hall November 5, 1684 / by Francis Lord Bishop of Ely ...</title>
                  <author>Turner, Francis, 1638?-1700.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 31 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Benj. Tooke ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Romans III, 8 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Louis Goldberg</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:56824:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:56824:1"/>
            <p> A SERMON Preached before the KING AT WHITE-HALL, <hi>November</hi> 5. 1684.</p>
            <p>BY <hi>FRANCIS</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>ELY,</hi> and Almoner to His Majeſty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by His Maieſties Special Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Benj. Tooke,</hi> at the <hi>Ship</hi> in S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard. M DC LXXXV.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:56824:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:56824:2"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>ROM. cap. III. ver. viij.</bibl>
               <q>
                  <p>And not rather as we be ſlande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly reported, and as ſome affirm that we ſay, Let us do Evil that Good may come? Whoſe damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is juſt.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IF ever that grievous complaint, which in the foregoing Chapter S. <hi>Paul</hi> makes of the <hi>Jews,</hi> might be alſo made of ſome that call themſelves <hi>Chriſtians, The name of God is Blaſphemed among the Gentiles through you,</hi> perhaps from the time of S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s writing this Epiſtle to the time when the <hi>fifth of November,</hi> was firſt a Day of <hi>Note</hi> in our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Calendar, neither the Jewiſh nor Chriſtian ſtory can point out a more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable Inſtance of a great ſcandal gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven to all the World, than was that <hi>foul Conſpiracy</hi> which gave us occaſion of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:56824:3"/> Celebrating this as a <hi>Feſtival Day;</hi> yes, I may ſafely, that is, truly ſay, this was the greateſt ſcandal on the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> name within that compaſs of time: from S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Preaching <hi>the Goſpel of Peace,</hi> to the opening of this <hi>bloudy ſcene,</hi> there hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd nothing like this; nothing ſo ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nominious not only to Religion and to pretences of Piety, but to humane Nature it ſelf, nothing ſo full of <hi>black Diabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical malice:</hi> For the firſt good Friday, (as I may call it) was before that period of time which I ſet from S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtleſhip; then for the other <hi>Judas</hi>'s and the later <hi>Pilates</hi> that occaſioned our ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting apart the 30<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>January</hi> for our <hi>ſolemn Faſt,</hi> they liv'd and flouriſht a great while after theſe goodly forerunners and worthy Leaders of theirs the <hi>Powder-Traitors.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what ſhall we ſay when S. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf is forc't to enter his Proteſtation in my <hi>Text,</hi> and make his appeal to all the World in a caſe of <hi>ſcandal,</hi> which though never given by him, yet was taken up againſt him by ſome either <hi>Jews</hi> or
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:56824:3"/> 
               <hi>Judaizing Chriſtians,</hi> or <hi>Gnoſtick Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks,</hi> by ſuch men as theſe <hi>was the name of Chriſt Blaſphemed among the Gentiles through him,</hi> through S. <hi>Paul the Apoſtle of the Gentiles,</hi> theſe ſtriving to faſten it upon him and his fellow-helpers in the Goſpel, ſo as by conſequence to fix it upon Chriſt himſelf, as if it were a part of that Goſpel, and a piece of true Chriſtian Divinity, Preacht up as a good Principle, <hi>Let us do evil that good may come of it;</hi> a Principle which if granted may ſerve to juſtify any malicious wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, nay even to glorify thoſe that acted in the <hi>Prodigious Wickedneſs</hi> of this Day. Now after ſuch a Calumny as this, that any ſhould affirm this, as if S. <hi>Paul</hi> had ſaid it or did approve it, what Man, or what order of Men can expect or hope to eſcape being ſlanderouſly reported?</p>
            <p>But how was this occaſion taken if none were given to defame this glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Saint and Servant of Jeſus Chriſt, and through his ſides to ſtrike at the Honour of his Maſter? Be pleas'd to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> had upon all oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:56824:4"/> magnified the goodneſs of God in ſending the Goſpel to thoſe, who could leaſt expect ſuch an unſpeakable Gift of a Divine Revelation, ſince they had offended all manner of ways againſt the Dictates of Nature and right Reaſon, as well as againſt the ſufficient Grace vouchſaf't them: But upon this very ſcore does S. <hi>Paul</hi> extol the Mercy of God to them, that <hi>where ſin had abounded, there Grace had ſuperabounded.</hi> But from this ſaying of His, this Great ſaying, ſome took advantage to raiſe an odious lye upon him, as if he had declared him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the caſe of the <hi>Pagans</hi> having the Goſpel preacht to them; that ſince the greatneſs of their ſins did make God's mercy appear the more viſibly great and glorious in ſending the Goſpel to ſuch, therefore it was lawful to live vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious heatheniſh Lives, the more to il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrate the glory of that Grace in the forgiveneſs of ſuch monſtrous foul of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fences. For anſwer to this Calumny, though he can ſcarce afford to anſwer it, but with indignation rejects it as a
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:56824:4"/> wicked ſlander; he that in another place had ſhew'd ſo much charity as to <hi>wiſh himſelf an Anathema for his Brethren,</hi> the deluded <hi>Jews,</hi> on condition they might be <hi>converted;</hi> yet he denounces here an <hi>Anathema</hi> upon thoſe <hi>Slanderers,</hi> who (it may be ſuppos'd) wilfully had perverted the Doctrine of <hi>Chriſtianity: their Damnation,</hi> he declares, is <hi>Juſt</hi> and Righteous, if they perſevere in charging not only him but his Bleſſed Goſpel with admitting ſo curſed a Principle, as if it were lawful to <hi>do</hi> any one known <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil,</hi> though with an eye to the beſt and nobleſt Deſigns, and with an aim at no other conſequences but ſuch as were moſt beneficial to the Publick; nay though the Glory of God, the propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gating of his Goſpel, the ſetling of his Church, be the ſtudied end and intent of that one <hi>forbidden Action:</hi> it muſt not be allowed in contemplation of all the good in the World.</p>
            <p>But ſince the Apoſtle has ſaid enough to vindicate himſelf, that this was no <hi>Apoſtolical Canon</hi> of his Making, but
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:56824:5"/> rather a Maxime from Hell (and thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he ſends it again) I ſhall now conſider it apart, and drawing off from the particular caſe of S. <hi>Paul,</hi> I ſhall pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed by theſe ſteps which will come extremely home to the caſe of theſe ſinners againſt their own Souls, whoſe burthen it is to be arraign'd every <hi>fifth of November.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt I ſhall ſhew that this Principle, of <hi>doing Evil that good may come of it,</hi> does indeed afford a colour (though a falſe deceitful colour) to thoſe that <hi>do Evil to call it Good,</hi> and ſo to go on as if they did no <hi>Evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, that this is a moſt unchri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian heatheniſh Principle, <hi>Let us do evil that good may come of it:</hi> accordingly the Apoſtle has read their ſentence, whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever they are that hold it, <hi>their damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is Juſt;</hi> and ſtill the more juſt their damnation, as they juſtify the more impious Practices upon this Principle; where I ſhall have occaſion to ſhew how thoſe that acted in this <hi>helliſh Conſpiracy</hi> proceeded upon this Principle, and by
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:56824:5"/> conſequence, how juſtly they fell into condemnation.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That it is a wicked Slander, to charge any that are not guilty, as if they held this Principle, or proceeded upon it in their Practices: Now, whereas we of the Church of <hi>England</hi> do charge ſome others that are not of the <hi>Roman</hi> Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, and whereas we our ſelves are charged by ſome, <hi>as if we alſo were ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Turns</hi> upon this ſame Principle, I ſhall endeavour to make it appear, who are, and who are not <hi>ſlanderouſly Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, I ſhall ſhew, that this Principle, of <hi>Doing Evil, that Good may come of it,</hi> does indeed afford a Colour (though a falſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitful Colour) to thoſe that <hi>do Evil to call it Good,</hi> and ſo to go on as if they <hi>did no Evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wo unto them that call Evil Good, and Good Evil</hi> (ſayes the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah)</hi> then Wo unto them that take up this Principle, <hi>of Doing Evil that Good may come of it;</hi> for Evil when it is called by its own Name, and when it appears in its own ſhape, is ſo frightful a thing, few can
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:56824:6"/> endure the ſight of it in themſelves, till they have borrow'd for it a Mask from Goodneſs. Now of all the Diſguiſes capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Cheating the Judgement, none is ſo proper as this, a great Deſign ſeemingly for the Glory of God; an End ſo good, as to be thought a ſufficient Apology, a fair Excuſe for the bad Means us'd to attain it. This is ſo forcible a Motive <hi>to do Evil that Good may come of it,</hi> that in the Heat of ſuch a Temptation, as comes but once, and unexpectedly, a Man of true Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, (when to uſe the words of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Ezekiel, God layes a ſtumbling block be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him,</hi> either for his Tryal, or his Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment) even one that <hi>walks warily with God,</hi> may make a falſe ſtep ſometimes in ſome more Difficult and more Diſputable Caſes, though upon ſecond thoughts and cooler Debates, he preſently ſees his Error: So S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> in his Treatiſe <hi>De Mendacio,</hi> where he does very rationally conclude all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of <hi>Serious Officious Lying,</hi> to be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely <hi>unlawful,</hi> though it were to preſerve a Life, (the Life of a Saint whom a Tyrant ſought to diſcover and put to
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:56824:6"/> death) nay, though it were to ſave a ſoul, yet he does acknowledge his own want of Reſolution in ſome hard Caſes and ſurprizing Exigences, when his Truth happens to ſtand in Competition with his Compaſſion, and he cannot do ſome great Good, or avoid ſome deſperate Evil, without admitting that, which he ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly calls <hi>Quaſi Compenſativum Peccatum, a ſin that ſeems to make amends for it ſelf.</hi> It does but <hi>ſeem</hi> to do ſo. But then if the beſt men have been prevail'd withal to tranſgreſs upon this account in leſſer In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances, no wonder if the worſt men <hi>do Evil with both hands,</hi> the greateſt Evil, when they have it in their proſpect, or, which is all one, in their fancy, to compaſs by ſo doing the greateſt Good; when they have an Enthuſiaſm upon them, and are poſſeſt, that as they Act <hi>for</hi> God and his Glory, ſo they Act <hi>like</hi> Him too, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly as He does: they mean <hi>to bring Light out of Darkneſs,</hi> even out of their own <hi>deeds of Darkneſs;</hi> when they are conſulting and contriving to raiſe a New World of Order and Beauty, out of that Chaos and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:56824:7"/> Confuſion, to which they muſt firſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce all things. This is the Principle ſtill that is at the bottom of all that <hi>Evil under the Sun</hi> committed by ſuch as S. <hi>Paul</hi> foretells there ſhall come in <hi>theſe laſt dayes, in theſe perillous times, men that are Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, heady, high-minded.</hi> Such <hi>Traytors</hi> as are Elevated and even Tranſported with the Glory (though it be but vain Glory) of ſome high flying Deſign in their preſent management; ſuch <hi>Traytors</hi> as propoſe ſome vaſt Undertaking as a Common Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefaction: Such are apt to conceit they have made themſelves neceſſary, as if God Almighty could not do his Work without them: then they conclude, they are ſo much before-hand with Him; that He is indebted to them <hi>an Indulgence</hi> for the groſſeſt Prevarications of His Laws; then to contradict the <hi>Reveal'd Will</hi> of God is Greatneſs and Priviledge, not Sin: So I have heard, that the Caſe of <hi>Jacob wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> with God, was Preacht upon to our late great Uſurper from that Text, <hi>Let me go, for the day breaketh: and he ſaid, I will not let thee go except thou bleſs me;</hi> whence there
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:56824:7"/> was rais'd this Doctrine moſt comfortable for <hi>him, That Gods</hi> Jacobs, <hi>or Glorious Wreſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers with God, might for great Ends do ſome things contrary to His Declar'd Will, which things might yet be Acceptable to His Secret Will, and procure a Bleſsing.</hi> Then they grow <hi>Maſters</hi> or <hi>Learned in Wickedneſs</hi> (as the Prophet <hi>Jeremy</hi> ſpeaks) they are Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minated with ſo Extraordinary Notions of Juſtice and Charity, that they have no Charity for other mens Underſtandings, but count <hi>them</hi> Tender-hearted <hi>Fools</hi> that oppoſe their <hi>Expedient,</hi> and therefore <hi>Meritorious</hi> Cruelties, with any Scruples of Pity. <hi>Ye know nothing at all</hi> (it was very Magiſterially ſpoken by <hi>Caiaphas</hi> the High Prieſt) <hi>nor conſider that it is Expedient for us, that One Man ſhould Dye for the People, and that the whole Nation Periſh not.</hi> Now if I can deſtroy this fundamentally Erroneous Principle of <hi>Expedience</hi> inſtead of that which is <hi>Juſt and Right,</hi> I ſhall plow up the very ground upon which the Architects of what ever Sect or Party do build almoſt all their Treaſonable Deſigns. I wiſh I could <hi>ſow it with Salt</hi> too, and that none
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:56824:8"/> might dare to build upon it hereafter, for fear of the <hi>Curſe</hi> that S. <hi>Paul</hi> has left on the Ground.</p>
            <p>I proceed then in the Second Place to ſhew, That this is a moſt Unchriſtian Heatheniſh Principle, <hi>Let us Do Evil that Good may come of It.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And Firſt, I ſhall make it appear, That whoever Act on this Principle, do but Abuſe themſelves and others, if they ſuppoſe that they Act for the Glory of God.</p>
            <p>Secondly, I ſhall Expoſe the neceſſary but extream ill Conſequence of this Principle, that it naturally leads from one great Sin and Miſchief to another.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That they do not Act for the Glory of God:</p>
            <p>For what can more tend to leſſen the Glory of an Omnipotent Being, and <hi>of purer Eyes than to behold Iniquity,</hi> than to break his moſt Holy Commandments upon pretence of doing Him Honour and Service; as if He could not Govern the World, but by Conniving at their Violation of His Precepts? But it may be
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:56824:8"/> anſwer'd for them, that perhaps they judge it <hi>no Iniquity,</hi> while they Intend all <hi>for his Glory:</hi> But 'tis eaſily reply'd, they do not ſincerely Intend it: They may <hi>think</hi> indeed that they do <hi>Intend</hi> it; they may not only to <hi>others</hi> ſeem to do ſo (which is as eaſie as <hi>winking</hi> to counterfeit <hi>ſleeping)</hi> but to <hi>themſelves;</hi> they may be men of that ſtrange Compoſition and Contradiction which S. <hi>Paul</hi> deſcribes, <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceivers and being deceived:</hi> They may be bloody Hypocrites, and yet imagine them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the bleſſed Inſtruments of God, and Workers for His Glory. Such were they of whom the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> gives this ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, <hi>Your Brethren that hated you and caſt you out for my Name ſake, ſaid, Let the Lord be Glorified.</hi> But notwithſtanding all this <hi>Deceitfulneſs</hi> of the Heart, we muſt come at laſt to this reſolution of the Caſe, That as the <hi>Stoick</hi> Philoſophy concludes all <hi>Evil-Doers</hi> to be <hi>Fools</hi> and <hi>Ignorant,</hi> though the violence of their <hi>Affections</hi> has wrought them up to the heighth of <hi>Perſwaſion that they do well;</hi> ſo the <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Philoſophy ſuppoſes all ſuch <hi>Fools,</hi> to be <hi>Knaves;</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:56824:9"/> all Chriſtians that are <hi>Ignorant</hi> of ſuch plain neceſſary Practical Doctrines, as <hi>to do no Murther</hi> on pretence of <hi>Doing God Service,</hi> muſt be ſuppos'd to be <hi>willingly Ignorant,</hi> as S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks: <hi>Willingly,</hi> that is, <hi>wilfully Ignorant</hi> if they be Chriſtians: <hi>For the works of the Fleſh are manifeſt,</hi> ſayes S. <hi>Paul:</hi> and amongſt thoſe works is <hi>Murther</hi> as well as <hi>Adultery:</hi> ſo that the Caſe of thoſe Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders who pretend to <hi>believe</hi> S. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, is altogether different from the Caſe of S. <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf, though his was bad enough too, while he was a Perſecutor of the Church, <hi>out of Zeal to the Glory of God,</hi> but <hi>yet he did it ignorantly in Unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lief.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But Secondly, (To joyn together both thoſe Conſiderations which I propoſed) A Principle that opens a Gap to let in Sin upon Sin, and Miſchief upon Miſchief, can never be a Means to advance the Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of God, or ſet forward the welfare of Mankind, unleſs the way to either of thoſe be to <hi>turn the World upſide down.</hi> That it opens a Gap, did I ſay, to let in Sin? Yes, it ſets the very Flood-gates of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:56824:9"/> Hell wide open, to pour upon the Earth a black Inundation of the moſt Practical Atheiſm, to which God alone can ſpeak, as He does to the Sea, <hi>Hitherto ſhalt thou go, and no farther.</hi> To prove it upon theſe <hi>Conſpirators of the Fifth of November,</hi> procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſtill upon this ſame ground; How did they, as <hi>David</hi> ſaid of other wicked men, <hi>go from one wickedneſs to another?</hi> From conſpiring a Horrible <hi>Maſſacre</hi> of ſo many reputed <hi>Hereticks,</hi> but moſt falſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſo call'd, they ſoon Reſolv'd it as Lawful to Murder many whom they judg'd to be altogether <hi>Innocent</hi> and Good <hi>Catholicks;</hi> yet even ſuch were Condemn'd to Fall with the <hi>Guilty He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks.</hi> It was determin'd by <hi>Garnet</hi> the <hi>Provincial,</hi> That even <hi>this was Lawful, if ſo much Good would come of it, as would Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſe the Lives of ſo many Guiltleſs Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons.</hi> So they ſupported themſelves on the ſame ground ſtill, <hi>Onmia metiri ex com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo Sanctae Matris Eccleſiae,</hi> to <hi>Meaſure all things by the Benefit would Accrue to their Holy Mother Church.</hi> Their Deſign they thought was <hi>Catholick,</hi> therefore it muſt be <hi>Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:56824:10"/> though it were attended throughout with the moſt Sacrilegious Abuſes of their Holy Things, <hi>Oaths, Confeſſions</hi> and <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And upon this account I call'd it a <hi>Helliſh Conſpiracy,</hi> for their Owning and Avowing a Doctrine ſo <hi>Damnable</hi> as this; (for ſo does S. <hi>Paul</hi> call it) the <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> or rather the <hi>Infernal Subtlety</hi> of Traytors; a <hi>Wiſdom,</hi> which to be ſure, <hi>deſcended not from Above:</hi> 'tis ſhort to call it <hi>Earthly</hi> and <hi>Senſual,</hi> unleſs I add the Apoſtles laſt Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thet, and call it <hi>Deviliſh.</hi> For, allowing them their utmoſt Rigours, their moſt unreaſonable Prejudices to our Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion; yet to Attempt our Reduction through a Sea of Blood, I muſt ſtill call it <hi>Deviliſh:</hi> This Reſtoring us (as they call it) to the Church, by Hurrying <hi>Kings</hi> and Princes out of the World, and Invol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving a whole <hi>Senate</hi> in Duſt and Blood; the Remedy is worſe than they can ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine the Diſeaſe: the Preſcription is as Unnatural as Deteſtable, as was the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of ſome Phyſicians, or rather Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gicians to the <hi>Royal Conſtantine,</hi> (if there be
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:56824:10"/> truth in the Story, however the Moral is good) that He might be cured of his Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie, if He would bathe Himſelf in the Life-blood of Infants: 'tis ſaid, He ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horr'd the Medicine: and I wiſh that Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> who they pretend cured this Emperour of his Leproſie when he Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiz'd Him (though the Lye be long ago rejected and derided by the Learned of their own Church, I wiſh he) could have Entail'd but ſo much Tenderneſs upon all his Succeſſors in that See, that they ſhould not have thought of Purging us to Death, when we were in ſo good health; then would they not by their <hi>Depoſing</hi> or <hi>Excluding Bulls</hi> have given Life to ſuch a Deſign as this, of <hi>waſhing</hi> us, by <hi>ſhed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Royal Blood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have ſhew'd how thoſe that Acted in this <hi>Conſpiracy,</hi> proceeded upon this Principle <hi>of Doing Evil that Good may come of it,</hi> and by conſequence, how juſtly they fell into Condemnation: But now, whereas we our ſelves of the <hi>Church of England</hi> charge ſome others that are not of the <hi>Roman Communion,</hi> and whereas we our ſelves are charged by
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:56824:11"/> ſome, as if we alſo were <hi>ſerving Turns</hi> upon this ſame Principle; I ſhall in the Third and laſt Place, and that very briefly, endeavour to make it appear, <hi>who are,</hi> and who are <hi>not ſlanderouſly Reported.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Since I undertook to ſhew the ſpreading malignant Influence of this Principle, can I avoid reflecting on another Party? when ever they Heard or Read the <hi>Story</hi> of the <hi>Powder-Traytors,</hi> ſure they muſt needs Reflect upon themſelves in ſuch words as thoſe which immediately follow my Text, <hi>What then? are we better than they? no, in no wiſe.</hi> I mean the Party that open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Voted and Acted in <hi>Weſtminſter-Hall</hi> the Unparallel'd Villany, which they Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at <hi>White-Hall-Gate:</hi> And perhaps it were an Exceſs of Charity, to ſuppoſe that any of them ever Imagin'd or Intended <hi>any Good to come of it,</hi> but only to ſet up themſelves, which was another Inſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table <hi>Evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I muſt needs add, Has not the ſame reſtleſs <hi>Party</hi> gone on ſtill, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon the ſame Principle, or none at all? Should they not in all Reaſon and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:56824:11"/> Conſcience, when ever they talk of theſe <hi>Regicides of the Fifth of November,</hi> ask them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the ſame plain Queſtion, and give themſelves the ſame Anſwer? <hi>What then? are we better than they? no, in no wiſe.</hi> For ſure the Crime is much alike, whether a King be Deſtroy'd at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> or the <hi>Rye,</hi> whether by ſo many <hi>Barrels of Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> or ſo <hi>many Blunderbuſſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But farther yet: Muſt we not ſadly Acknowledge, that there is a <hi>Numerous Party,</hi> who, though I hope and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, they are none of the <hi>Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors,</hi> yet by following the <hi>grain</hi> of this Principle, <hi>Doing Evil that Good may come of it,</hi> they are in a fair way to be any thing, rather than Chriſtians? Is it not come to that paſs, that many will rather <hi>forſwear</hi> themſelves, <hi>than Act againſt their Conſcience</hi> (as they call it) or which is all one with them, <hi>againſt their Party?</hi> Is not <hi>Caſuiſtical Divinity</hi> grown even in this Age and Nation, as One ingeniouſly defin'd it, <hi>Ars litigandi cum Deo, an Art of trying Cauſes with God Almighty; a ſtudy to make every thing that men have a mind to do, as Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful</hi>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:56824:12"/> 
               <hi>as they can?</hi> God has given us <hi>ten Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments,</hi> and we return Him <hi>ten Expedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents,</hi> and <hi>twenty Shifts,</hi> inſtead of <hi>Obeying</hi> Him. 'Tis commonly ſaid among thoſe that know how to Adapt and Apply the <hi>Jeſuits Salvo's</hi> according to any preſent Exigency, <hi>That a Man of Wit never ſins againſt his Conſcience;</hi> for he can ſhew the Caſe in ſuch Lights, as to make it look fairly to himſelf. But are the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> the only <hi>Favourable Caſuiſts</hi> to themſelves? Was there not publiſht, and that not long ago, a Treatiſe <hi>on Occaſional Communion?</hi> and then another Treatiſe, ſtating that Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion about <hi>taking the Oaths and Sacrament,</hi> to Qualifie <hi>Diſſenters</hi> for <hi>Publick Truſts?</hi> Who ever reads thoſe Pieces, and remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers what Excellent uſe was made of that Doctrine, muſt needs confeſs, that there are men in the World, who cry <hi>the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant, the Proteſtant,</hi> as loud as ever the <hi>Jews</hi> did <hi>the Temple of the Lord, the Temple of the Lord;</hi> or as the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> do <hi>the Church, the Catholick Church;</hi> and yet theſe <hi>True Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants,</hi> (as they love to ſtyle themſelves) are <hi>truly and thoroughly Jeſuited</hi> in the <hi>Arts</hi>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:56824:12"/> 
               <hi>of Evaſion,</hi> deſtructive to the End of our <hi>Laws,</hi> and contrary to the meaning of our <hi>Law-Givers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus all men would do ſomething <hi>to ſave their Souls,</hi> (as we ſay,) or they would at leaſt ſay ſomething <hi>to ſave their Credit</hi> with themſelves as well as with others: Some Device they would gladly find out to eaſe themſelves, while they play with that little of <hi>Natural Conſcience</hi> they have left them. They do, like one that forg'd a Will, then took up the Dead Body out of the Grave, put a Pen into the Dead man's Hand, guided the Hand to ſign the Will, and then took his Oath, that he had ſeen it ſign'd by the Hand of the Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. To what purpoſe was all this Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geantry? Had not down-right Perjury been as eaſily ſwallowed? No; Drow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning men will catch at Straws: Such is the force of Religion, that it can ſcarce be abſolutely ſtifl'd in the minds of men; they would gladly retain ſome faint colour or ſhadow of Innocence, that their faults may not appear too ugly, but that they may
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:56824:13"/> 
               <hi>flatter themſelves in their own ſight, until their Abominable Sin be found out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But what do we of the <hi>Church of England</hi> complain of others, if that be true which ſome would fain inſinuate, that we are <hi>Betraying our ſelves?</hi> Why do we ſtill thank God for Diſcovering and Defeating <hi>the Powder-Plot,</hi> if we are <hi>Undermining the</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Several of Mr. <hi>Pryn</hi>'s Pieces, <hi>Apoſtaſia Laudenſium. Patronus Bonae Fidei,</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Church?</hi> for we are <hi>ſo Reported,</hi> whether <hi>ſlanderouſly</hi> or no, muſt be tryed: What Volumes have been Publiſht heretofore, and ſome Pamphlets but lately, to make it appear, <hi>that Arch-Biſhop</hi> Laud <hi>had bred us up for Popery?</hi> What a noiſe has been made with this, as if they meant to ſtop the Cry of his Innocent Blood with their Clamours, that he Liv'd and Dy'd in the Deſign of Introducing Popery? Nay more, that the <hi>Governing part of the preſent Clergy,</hi> have made what Advances they could, treading in his footſteps, and in the ſame Broad Way, with their Faces to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the <hi>Vatican.</hi> The Clergy of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> are more than Ten Thouſand Men; that moſt of this vaſt Number, (whether
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:56824:13"/> they <hi>Lead</hi> or <hi>Drive)</hi> ſhould be marching ſo faſt toward <hi>Rome,</hi> is exceeding ſtrange. It puts me in mind of the Story of <hi>the Eleven Thouſand Virgins,</hi> who, as the <hi>Legend</hi> would make us believe, went out of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> in Pilgrimage, and Periſht in the way. But the Wiſeſt and Learnedeſt Writers for that Fable, would be conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to ſtrike out their <hi>thouſands</hi> at firſt daſh; that they confeſs was an Error of ſome Monkiſh Tranſcriber; they would gladly compound for <hi>Eleven,</hi> nor can they prove even thoſe few: So may not I challenge all our Accuſers, that reflect on ſo great a Body as the <hi>Clergy,</hi> which conſiſt (as I ſaid) <hi>of ten thouſand</hi> at leaſt; <hi>To name but ten of the whole Clergy; ten men of any Note, either for their Dignity or Learning, who in the worſt of Times, under the greateſt Temptations, fell from the</hi> Church of England <hi>to that of Rome?</hi> But ſince we are ſo Defam'd, as if we ſtill went on with the ſame <hi>Intrigue,</hi> where that <hi>Great Prelate</hi> was forc't to leave off, in Vindicating Him, I ſhall make a Defence for our ſelves, and to Juſtifie Him
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:56824:14"/> and His Adminiſtration, I ſhall make ſuch an <hi>Appeal to Rome</hi> it ſelf, as will be in no danger of a <hi>Praemunire.</hi> And firſt I refer my ſelf to a Voluminous <hi>Italian Writer of Univerſal Hiſtory,</hi> he Qualify'd himſelf very long ago with the Title of <hi>Hiſtorian to the Moſt Chriſtian King:</hi> His Name I <hi>ſpare,</hi> becauſe I think he is Living ſtill, though he <hi>ſpares</hi> not the <hi>Memory</hi> of the <hi>Dead,</hi> and of one that Dy'd a <hi>Martyr.</hi> This Author is pleas'd to conclude in theſe words the <hi>Tragical Story</hi> of that Great Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, <hi>Laying down his Head upon the Block, it was</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>ſever'd from his Shoulders by the Executioner at one Blow,</hi> Rendendo l'ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma a Satanaſſo, i. e. <hi>while he gave up his Soul to the Great Devil, to whom</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>he belong'd in his life time, with his Damnable Doctrine of</hi> Calvin, <hi>whoſe follower he was.</hi> While I live I ſhall think the better of our <hi>Charity in the Church of England,</hi> as often as I Reflect upon this moſt Uncharitable Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion: In the mean time, with what Juſtice is He ſtill <hi>branded</hi> by our <hi>Diſſenting Proteſtants</hi> for a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> when the other
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:56824:14"/> 
               <hi>Adverſe Party</hi> at the ſame time <hi>Damn</hi> Him for <hi>a Calviniſt?</hi> But I add further, with what Juſtice does this <hi>Romaniſt</hi> tax Him for a <hi>Calviniſt,</hi> when there's another <hi>far more Authentick Writer,</hi> a <hi>Romaniſt</hi> too, but <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Spondanus, Anno</hi> 1605.</note> of a more <hi>Chriſtian</hi> temper, (for he ſpeaks with Deteſtation of the <hi>Powder-Plot,</hi> and aſcribes the Diſcovery of it to the Hand of God:) &amp; this Author clearly <hi>acquits</hi> that Renowned Prelate both from <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Puritaniſm?</hi> I mean the <hi>Pope's own Hiſtorian</hi> (as I may ſtyle him) the <hi>Continuator of the Great Cardinals Annals,</hi> who gives this Account, <hi>the Primate of England</hi> (ſayes <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Spondanus, Anno</hi> 1645.</note> he) <hi>without the Tents of the Roman and Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolick Church, after he had been Impriſon'd in the</hi> Tower of London <hi>for many Months, is Beheaded by the Command of thoſe that ſtood for the Parliament, for his ſtanding up in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of the Kings Juſt Rights, and for Advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing his Majeſty againſt the Puritans:</hi> then it follows, <hi>Catholica Religio ei Morienti defuit, quod dolendum, He wanted the Catholick Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion when he dy'd, which</hi> (ſayes my Author, partial to his own Faction) <hi>was to be la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented.</hi>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:56824:15"/> By the <hi>Catholick,</hi> we are ſure he means the <hi>Roman.</hi> After two ſuch <hi>Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies</hi> as theſe, who ever can believe <hi>that Great and Good Man</hi> a <hi>Romaniſt,</hi> can, I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, believe whatever he has a mind to believe, and he may in good time <hi>believe</hi> the Relation of a Third Author, a <hi>Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ran German,</hi> who in the Body of a large <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Continuat. Pezelii pars</hi> 4. <hi>Mellif. Hiſt. Anno</hi> 1645.</note> General Hiſtory tells us gravely, that <hi>the Arch-Biſhop being Convicted to have Accepted the Title of a Cardinal ſent him by the Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of</hi> Oxford, <hi>and to have Corrupted Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, was put to Death.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And we are juſt as Guilty as he was: 'Tis true indeed, we refus'd to Cloſe and Comply with <hi>this Doctrine of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pedients;</hi> ſome of them not unlike <hi>Sampſon</hi>'s Deſperate <hi>Expedient</hi> to Deſtroy the <hi>Philiſtins,</hi> by pulling a <hi>vaſt Fabrick</hi> up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his own head, as we muſt have done the <hi>Monarchy</hi> upon ours; or rather, like <hi>Fawx</hi>'s <hi>Expedient</hi> to prevent the Death he apprehended, but to prevent it, <hi>by Blowing up the Parliament-Houſe and himſelf and all,</hi> which he much regretted he had not done then when they ſeiz'd upon him: 'Tis
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:56824:15"/> very true, we believ'd it a prepoſterous way of <hi>ſecuring our Religion,</hi> by giving up <hi>the peculiar Honour of our Church, the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Obedience unto Kings:</hi> And we judg'd it a <hi>ſtrange Means of Barring out Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pery, by letting in the Doctrine of Tranſlating and Diſpoſing of Kingdoms:</hi> 'Tis moſt true, <hi>we Abhorr'd that Aſſociation,</hi> which naturally and directly lead to <hi>the ſecond Powder-Plot,</hi> as I muſt have leave to call it: All this is true, and becauſe we in none of theſe Inſtances, would <hi>Do Evil for fear of ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering it,</hi> therefore <hi>we are Reported</hi> to be <hi>Doing</hi> or <hi>Deſigning</hi> ſo <hi>ill a thing,</hi> as 'tis hard to conceive, what <hi>Good</hi> we ſhould <hi>Intend,</hi> even to our <hi>private Intereſts,</hi> by hurting the <hi>publick:</hi> And therefore we may truly ſay with S. <hi>Paul</hi> in my Text, <hi>that we are ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derouſly Reported.</hi> And they that are Guil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the Slander do an Extream ill thing, whatever their Ends be: they might ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect <hi>ſome Good to come of it,</hi> if they could teach the Party, <hi>cum Ratione inſanire,</hi> that is, <hi>When they had frighted them with Fears and Jealouſies out of their Wits, then to make them</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:56824:16"/> 
               <hi>Act like Reaſonable Creatures.</hi> But if the <hi>Aſſociation</hi> had broken out into a <hi>furious Rebellion,</hi> (and that was juſt breaking out, as 'tis moſt clear and Evident, from many <hi>Credible Witneſſes,</hi> and <hi>Dying Confeſſions long ago,</hi> nay, <hi>from Hands and Seals taken but very lately)</hi> then how could the <hi>Greateſt Evil</hi> have been avoided? (even as <hi>Great</hi> as any that <hi>Piercy</hi> and <hi>Catesby</hi> intended) unleſs <hi>Well-meaning Rebells could have given every Bullet its Commiſſion, whom to hit or miſs, and could have directed their Shot as well as their Intentions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Soon after that <hi>Execrable Aſſaſſination</hi> of King <hi>Henry</hi> the Fourth of <hi>France,</hi> one of that Great Prince's Servants, one of that Incomparable Learning, as made him juſtly eſteem'd <hi>one of the Glories of his Time,</hi> coming over into <hi>England</hi> to divert his Melancholy, and to wait upon King <hi>James, the Patron of the Learned,</hi> he writes <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Cauſabon. Epiſt.</hi> 1612. <hi>Dan. Heinſ.</hi>
               </note> from hence to another Eminent Scholar in theſe words, <hi>That he was come</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>into the Iſland of the Happy, where I enjoy</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>this Conſolation, that I am not</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:56824:16"/> 
               <hi>Tormented with the ſight of thoſe wicked Fiends and Parricides;</hi> thoſe he means, who, he ſuppos'd, had Animated the Murder of his <hi>Royal Maſter, and then</hi> (ſayes he) <hi>I have this Comfort too, that in this Kingdom I ſee that Face of the Primitive Church, which I learn'd to know from the Writings of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Fathers.</hi> But had that Worthy Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Liv'd and Convers'd with us here until theſe <hi>Times,</hi> he muſt have endur'd, not only the <hi>Aſpect,</hi> but the <hi>almoſt Twenty Years Tyranny</hi> of as <hi>Curſed Furies</hi> among us, as any he left behind him in his own Countrey: and he muſt have beheld ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Woful Spectacle, <hi>the Church which he ſo much admir'd,</hi> in a manner <hi>Defac'd,</hi> or at leaſt, moſt ſadly <hi>Deform'd</hi> by them. And yet by the Mercy of God, neither <hi>the black Traytors of the Powder-Plot,</hi> nor <hi>the ſcarlet Traytors of the High Court of Juſtice,</hi> (tho' theſe latter prevail'd for a time) were able to Compaſs their utmoſt Helliſh Ends and Purpoſes; but we are once again, <hi>the Iſland of the Happy,</hi> if we but knew our Happineſs; and we are a <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom</hi>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:56824:17"/> again, <hi>where there is now to be ſeen the ſame Venerable Face of the Ancient Church, Reſtor'd together with the King,</hi> and <hi>Reſtor'd by the King under God.</hi> As long as our <hi>Church</hi> deſerves that Glorious Character, which that <hi>Great Man</hi> beſtow'd upon it, <hi>while it bears the likeneſs of the Primitive Church,</hi> it has a Juſt Title to a full ſhare in that <hi>Gracious Promiſe</hi> made to the <hi>Catholick Church, Iſa.</hi> 54. and the laſt Verſe, <hi>No Wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon that is form'd againſt thee ſhall proſper, this is the Inheritance of the ſervants of the Lord;</hi> and may we not juſtly ſay with Joyful Thanks, <hi>that the Lot is fall'n to us in a fair Ground, and that this is a Goodly In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance?</hi> May we not with an Humble Greatneſs call ſuch a Church, <hi>the place of the Vineyard that His right hand hath planted; and the Branch that He made ſo ſtrong for Himſelf?</hi> O let it never be ſaid, <hi>that Her Hedge is broken down, that all they that go by pluck off her Grapes, that the Wild Boar out of the Wood doth Root it up, and the Wild Beaſts of the Field devour it.</hi> And after this Prayer for the Church, let us alſo pray
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:56824:17"/> for the King, as it follows in that Pſalm, <hi>Let thy Hand be upon the Man of thy Right Hand;</hi> or in the plainer words of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Pſalm, <hi>O continue thy Loving Mercies, that they may preſerve Him! So will we alway give praiſe unto thy Name, that we may daily perform our Vows.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now unto the King Eternal, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
